<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-01T22:41:10+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Robert Soane</title><subtitle>I'm a postgraduate student at the University of Nottingham, currently  studying for an MSc in Computer Science.  I graduated with a BSc (Hons) in Mathematics in 2020, having spent three years studying numerical  methods and applied maths.</subtitle><author><name>Robert</name></author><entry><title type="html">Pyfighter</title><link href="/2020/12/18/Pyfighter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pyfighter" /><published>2020-12-18T13:14:13+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-18T13:14:13+00:00</updated><id>/2020/12/18/Pyfighter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/12/18/Pyfighter.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A long time ago in a galaxy far, far away there existed in person tuition.  But in the year 2020, COVID struck.  All semester modules have been 100% online and you haven’t seen your professors.  So do they exist?  Are they just a figment of your imagination?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To cut costs, the university created AI professors to deliver your lectures and set your coursework.  Exam season approaches and the evil Darth Virus has hacked your professors, multiplying them and making your exams harder.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Only you can save your degree…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cAWdl9GXIeg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-game&quot;&gt;The Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pyfighter is an 8-bit side scrolling, infinite level platform game, produced in python using PyGame as part on an MSc by R. Soane, R. Danevicius, and S. Mistry.  Inspired by super street fighter, super smash bros and Mario, they created a customisable and addictive game that gets progressively harder.  Pyfighter was &lt;a src=&quot;https://github.com/robertpsoane/py-fighter/blob/master/runner_up_certificate.pdf&quot;&gt;ranked second of all games&lt;/a&gt; submitted and graded &lt;em&gt;distinction&lt;/em&gt; - 89%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;main-menu&quot;&gt;Main Menu&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On loading the game, you are met with the main menu.  The play button will lead you to an intro cutscene followed by the game, while settings opens the settings menu.  You can quit game from here, and the about button leads to this web page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;gameplay&quot;&gt;Gameplay&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gameplay is relatively simple, use the WASD keys to move your character and the space bar to attack. When all the characters in the level have been defeated a message will appear that the level is complete, and press e to move to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game can be paused by pressing the escape key at any time, which will load the pause menu. From here you can continue gameplay, quit game or quit to main menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The score is calculated based on number of health points taken by the character, vs number of health points the character takes. Each point the character takes equates to 1 point, and every 5 health points the character loses loses them 1 point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;settings&quot;&gt;Settings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the settings menu you can change the key bindings to your preferred set.  To do this simply press the change button next to the corresponding action.  The action text will highlight in red.  Press the key on your keyboard that you would like to set the action to and the binding will be updated.  To change the background track, simply press the music button at the bottom and it will iterate through the available tracks.  To return to the default settings, press the reset button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source code be downloaded free of charge from &lt;a href=&quot;http://download.pyfighter.xyz&quot;&gt;download.pyfighter.xyz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The windows installer can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robertpsoane/py-fighter/releases/download/v1.0.0/pyfighter_installer.exe&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installation-and-requirements&quot;&gt;Installation and Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To play Pyfighter you need the following installations on your system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python 3, with version &amp;gt;= 3.8.5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PyGame version &amp;gt;= 2.0.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;windows&quot;&gt;Windows&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download python from the downloads page of the python website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install pygame (required to play the game), run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install pygame&lt;/code&gt; from the command line. This will install the latest version of pygame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you already have an older version of pygame installed on your computer you will need to upgrade it to play.  To do this, run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install pygame==2.0.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game can then be run by running pyfighter.py from the projects root directory, or by double clicking the pyfighter.py icon from within Windows explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;linux&quot;&gt;Linux&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pyfighter has been tested on Ubuntu 20.04, but should run on other flavours of linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensure python3 is installed on your system, if it is not installed, run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo apt-get install python3&lt;/code&gt;, or use your favourite package manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install pygame, run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip3 install pygame&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give execute permissions, make sure to run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;chmod +x pyfighter.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python3 pyfighter.py&lt;/code&gt; from the projects root directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mac-os&quot;&gt;Mac OS&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been unable to test this project on Mac OS, however as it has been tested on various flavours of Linux we see no reason why it should fail on a mac.
Ensure python3 and pygame 2 are installed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">A long time ago in a galaxy far, far away there existed in person tuition. But in the year 2020, COVID struck. All semester modules have been 100% online and you haven’t seen your professors. So do they exist? Are they just a figment of your imagination?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Othello (GUI)</title><link href="/2020/12/02/Othello_gui.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Othello (GUI)" /><published>2020-12-02T13:14:13+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-02T13:14:13+00:00</updated><id>/2020/12/02/Othello_gui</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/12/02/Othello_gui.html">&lt;p&gt;This side project was to produce a fully functional GUI Othello engine. This was initially set as a challenge during an MSc tutorial to produce an Othello engine using minimax. I built a working engine (initially in the command line) and have since produced a GUI for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I redesigned it using a GUI, I decided to attempt to implement MVC, as a way of learning MVC. This could also make it easier to further extend the game in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-play&quot;&gt;How To Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim and of the game is simple - to have the most discs of your colour on the board at the end of the game.
The rules are also relatively simple.  On your turn you can play one disc on any square which is adjacent to an opponents disc, providing it is possible to ‘draw a straight line’ between your disc, and another of your discs, with all squares inbetween the two discs of your colour occupied by your opponents colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tactics&quot;&gt;Tactics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this sounds relatively simple, there are some general strategy points worth considering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The corners are the strongest positions, as they cannot be taken.  If you can place a piece on a corner, do so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next strongest positions are the squares along the edges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid placing any pieces one step in from a corner if you can help it, as this often makes it easier for your opponents to claim the corner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to minimise the number of moves your opponent can make, while maximising the number of moves you can make.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-modes&quot;&gt;Game Modes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This game comes with 3 game modes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play as Black: Play as black against the computer playing as white&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play as White: Play as white against the computer playing as black&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play PvP: Two players playing at the same board at the same computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-engine&quot;&gt;The engine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engine is playing using a minimax strategy (currently set at depth 5).
It attempts to follow the tactics listed above.  It does this by minimising future moves for its opponent, while maximising them for itself, then applying a points-based grading strategy to the board for each leaf of the tree.
The grading strategy is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[   [10, -2, 2, 2, 2, 2, -2, 10],
    [-2, -2, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, -2],
    [2, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 2],
    [2, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 2],
    [2, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 2],
    [2, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 2],
    [-2, -2, 1, 1, 1, 1, -2, -2],
    [10, -2, 2, 2, 2, 2, -2, 10]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The points are centered around 0, with a positive score meaning the engine has
the advantage, and a negative score meaning the player has an advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">This side project was to produce a fully functional GUI Othello engine. This was initially set as a challenge during an MSc tutorial to produce an Othello engine using minimax. I built a working engine (initially in the command line) and have since produced a GUI for it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Brief History of Encryption</title><link href="/2020/10/29/cyber_report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Brief History of Encryption" /><published>2020-10-29T13:14:13+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-29T13:14:13+00:00</updated><id>/2020/10/29/cyber_report</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/10/29/cyber_report.html">&lt;p&gt;As an assignment for one of my MSc modules I had to produce a report on cyber security. I chose to focus on encryption methods.
This is the report I produced. It was graded &lt;em&gt;distinction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout history there have been necessities for people to send sensitive data, be that battle plans on a
road, or their credit card number online. In many instances the users do not want a third party to intercept 
the data they are sending. This is where encryption comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happens, there are records of encryption and
concealed secret messages being sent long before the
existance of internets and computers. These date as
far back as 1900 B.C., when early civilisations would
conceal messages pictorially [1], or by use of a scytale.
Also used was a class of cipher still discussed today -
the Substitution cipher.
This report discusses a few of the various uses of
encryption throughout history, how the method works,
and how it can be broken.
In section 2 we discuss prehistoric encryption, which
although no longer useful to secure information still
provide a good introduction to encryption. This is
followed by a discussion of the Enigma device used
by the Germans in the 1930’s and 1940’s in section 3.
We delve into how it works, and how it was cracked.
Finally in section 4 we discuss modern day encryption
methods, how they work, and their vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-pre-historic-networks&quot;&gt;2. Pre-Historic Networks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose a Roman General wished to invade a city. His
regiment is approaching from the north, while another
is approaching from the south. Suppose also that he
was required to make a last minute change to his battle
plan. &lt;em&gt;How should he alert the other regiment of the new
plan?&lt;/em&gt;. If he sent a messgenger with the now plans how
would he ensure that if his messenger was captured the
plans wouldn’t fall into enemy hands? He would need
a way to encrypt the information such that only he and
the other regiment can understand what is written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this may seem irrelevant to 21st computer
networks and vulnerabilities, it forms one of the earliest
examples of encryption (and potentially unwanted
decryption). This scenario could also model a simple
computer network. The General and his regiments can
be modelled as two communicating hosts, his battle
plans some sensitive information, and his messenger
on the open road, the signal on a wire. As such, it forms
a useful starting point for a discussion on encryption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;21-the-scytale&quot;&gt;2.1. The Scytale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scytale is a cipher often attributed to the Ancient
Greeks [2]. It is a cylindrical rod around which paper
was wrapped before writing across multiple folds of
paper [3].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/projects/cyber_report/scytale.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 75%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/b&gt; A Scytale [4]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would transpose the message on the paper such
that it could only be read if wrapped around a rod of
the same diameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While easy to encode a message in this way, it is not
particularly secure. A third party can see by the nature
of the medium used (a long strip of paper) how the
message was encoded, and by trial and error decrypt
the message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;22-substitution-ciphers&quot;&gt;2.2. Substitution Ciphers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Merriam-Webster, a substitution cipher
is ‘a cipher in which the letters of the plaintext are
systematically replaced by substitute letters’ [5]. These
substitute letters are generally referred to as ciphertext.
A prominent example of a substitution cipher is the
Caesar cipher. This cipher was allegedly used by Julius
Caesar to encode sensitive military information [6],
hence its name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/projects/cyber_report/caesar.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 75%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 2:&lt;/b&gt; A Caesar Cipher with &lt;em&gt;key = 2&lt;/em&gt;, based on Figure 1
from Three-Pass Protocol Implementation in Caesar
Cipher Classic Cryptography [7]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown in figure 2, a Caesar cipher works by shifting
 each letter k spaces in the alphabet. This produces
a mapping which could easily and methodically be
applied to the message, the outcome looking like a
jumbled string of text. The number of characters by
which the message has been shifted is referred to as
the ‘key’. Any recipient of the message, could easily
reverse the mapping by that number of spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A result of its relative simplicity, is that the Caesar cipher
 is relatively simple to crack, and certainly isn’t sophisticated
  enough for modern day needs. As the cipher
is cyclical, there are only 25 possible keys. An obvious
and simple brute force method would be to attempt a
decryption using each key k = 1, k = 2, …k = 25 and
select whichever solution seems most realistic given
the circumstances. Any moderm computer could crack
this quite quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple knowledge of the given language, can speed
up this significantly, for example if we wished to decode
the following ‘K co vjg dguv fwem’, and we know that
‘I’ and ‘a’ are the most likely one letter words in English,
we could guess the key is probably +2 or +102
If we
guessed +10, and decrypted using −10, we would get
‘A se lzw twkl vmuc’, which is nonsense, however if
we decrypted using −2, we would get ‘I am the best
duck’. With one assumption, we have decrypted this
message in two attempts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any data encrypted with this method is relatively
easy to crack manually. With a computer, we would be
able to crack it in seconds. In section 3, a more complex
encryption method (with significant consequences) is
discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-the-enigma-and-the-bombe&quot;&gt;3. The Enigma and The Bombe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Second World War, similar to our Roman exam-
ple in section 2, the Germans were required to send&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;information across long distances, however they didn’t
use messengers, they used telegraph. Telegraph is a
form of communcation developed in the mid 1800’s by
Samuel Morse which relies on sending long and short
pulses in morse code [8]. Due to the unencrypted
nature of a telegraph signal, its use for transmitting
sensitive military information was only viable if there
was a way of reliably encrypting the data being sent,
and transmitting. As discussed in section 3.1, this is
exactly what the Germans did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;31-the-working-of-the-enigma&quot;&gt;3.1. The Working of The Enigma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Enigma machine was invented in 1919 by Hugo
Koch [9], and adopted by the German armed forces
to encode all messages before transmitting them. The
Germans believed this system to be unbreakable, and
that any Enigma-encrypted messages couldn’t be read
others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/projects/cyber_report/enigma.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 75%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 3:&lt;/b&gt;A labelled photograph of an Enigma machine [10]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enigma machine has four main parts. The keyboard,
 lampboard, plugboard, and the rotors (labelled
in figure 3). The working of an Enigma is simple. When
you press a button on the keyboard, a light on the
lampboard for a different letter is illuminated. One
would type the message they wished to encode into the
keyboard, recording each letter in the process. These
encrypted letters could then be transmitted by telegraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the device’s foreboding reputation, the inner
workings of the Enigma machine is relatively simple.
Each time a letter button is pressed, a signal travels
through the plugboard (a board where all letters in the
alphabet are paired with one other) transforming it to a
second letter, through the rotors where it is scrambled
to a third letter, back through that letters wire on the
plugboard where it is transformed to a fourth letter,
which then lights up. To complicate matters further,
each time a letter is pressed, the rotors increment one
step - if you press a letter multiple times in a row, you
would get different outputs each time (for this reason
the code couldn’t be broken as in section 2.2) [11]. The
recipient could input the coded output into a machine
set up the same (and operating in reverse) and they
would be able to read the message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/projects/cyber_report/RSA.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 75%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 4:&lt;/b&gt;A diagram showing how the electrical signal travels
in an Enigma machine based on image on Crypto
Museum [12]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To crack this code, and read messages being transmitted by the German military, all the Allies needed
was to guess the set-up of the machine. However there
were a few problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were approximately 150∗10&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt; possible com-
binations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Germans changed the setup on a daily basis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply guessing the starting position of the enigma
was not a reliable method of cracking the code. A
systematic approach was needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;32-the-bombe&quot;&gt;3.2. The Bombe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While impractical to crack manually by brute force, the
enigma had 2 significant vulnerabilities which were
exploited by British and Polish codebreakers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No letter ever mapped to itself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Messages sent by the Germans frequently included
standard strings of text, (such as greetings and
weather reports)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two vulnerabilities could be used in tandem
to systematically crack the code. By positioning the
standard string such that no letter mapped to itself, the
codebreakers could take the known string, compared
with the intercepted string to find a possible position
for the weather report within the ciphertext [13].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given their initial mapping, they could choose an
ansatz for the rotors, and proceed to systematically
work through the permeatations of the plugboard and
rotors until they have cracked the code. This process is
explained very well in the Numberphile YouTube video
Flaw in the Enigma Code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/V4V2bpZlqx8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method would still be impractical to complete
every day in time to decrypt all intercepted telegraphs.
To break the code on a daily basis, Alan Turing built
a machine which used electrical current to simulate
each possible setup permeatation of the plugboard and
drums which would act as rotors on the enigma [14].
In the internet age, encryption messages such as
the Enigma in this section, and the caesar cipher from
the previous section are unsuitable to send information
 securely. Section 4 discusses internet age uses of
encryption, and its vulnerabilities and controversies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-internet-age-encryption&quot;&gt;4. Internet Age Encryption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, we have discussed critical uses of encryption
in the past, and the significant effects vulnerabilities
have had. This section focuses on modern day uses of
encryption on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;41-why-encrypt&quot;&gt;4.1. Why Encrypt?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following two scenarios present examples of how
unencrypted data can introduce severe vulnerabilities
in systems, leaving systems open to attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suppose an online shopper wishes to make a purchase.
They input their debit card details into a
form, and click pay. Their details are sent across
the internet to the shop. Suppose someone was
listening, and could read the message being sent
from the shopper to the shop. They would then
have the customers details, and be able to steal
the customers money.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suppose an email account provider stores all their
users passwords in plaintext. Suppose an SQL
injection attack is carried out revealing all user
details on the database. The attacker would then
have access to all usernames and passwords in the
database. They would be able to log in to any users
email address, and access their personal details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these scenarios could be avoided if the
providers had encrypted the data they were using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;42-advanced-encryption-standard&quot;&gt;4.2. Advanced Encryption Standard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) has been
the standard algorithm for encrypting data in the US
since 2001 [16]. The AES algorithm uses a 128, 192,
or 256 bit key to encrypt 128-bit blocks of text prior to
sending them. The AES algorithm is an extremely fast
algorithm for a computer to carry out, and would take
an average of 100 trillion years to crack by brute force
[17].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AES algorithm works by splitting a 128-bit (16
byte) message into a 4x4 matrix. This undergoes several
rounds of substitution and permeatation operations,
between which parts of the key are added to the
the matrix. The reciever knows the key, and reverses
the algorithm on each block of data [18].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the algorithm is extremely secure, and cannot
be cracked by brute force, it has one major flaw. It is
symmetric. This means that both the sender and the
receiver need to know the same key. For a shopper to
encrypt their bank details, they would need a way of
getting the key from the online shop. Again, if someone
were listening and intercepted the key, they would have
access to the data being sent. The customers bank
details would no longer be secure. So how can we
solve this problem? We need an asymmetric encryption
method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;43-rivest-shamir-alderman&quot;&gt;4.3. Rivest-Shamir-Alderman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rivest-Shamir-Alderman (RSA) algorithm is one of
the oldest and most well-known encryption algorithms.
It was released in 1977 by Ron Rivest, Adi Shamir and
Leonard Adleman [19]. The advantage of RSA of AES is
that RSA is an asymmetric method of encryption. That
is, data can be encrypted by one party, and decrypted
by the other without them both knowing the key. While
this sounds somewhat like magic or telepathy, the algorithm
 is in fact underpinned by number theory. In a
process which will be explained in section 4.3.1, two
keys are generated, a public, and a private key. The
public key is shared and used to encrypt the data, and
the private key is used to decrypt the data. Crucial to
RSA is that the encryption process cannot be reversed
with the public key - the private key is needed [20].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While RSA has a significant advantage over AES - it
is computationally more complex, and thus adds more
overheads to a data transfer. It is useful when small
amounts of data (such as a credit card number) need
transmitting, however for a long sessions it reduces
speed. It is however often used together with AES to
allow secure encrypted communication [21]. In figure
5, client A generates RSA keys, and sends the public key
to client B. Client B generates an AES key, which they
encrypt with the RSA public key. This can then be sent
to client A securely. Client A can decrypt the message
to find the AES key, which is then used throughout the
session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 75%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 5:&lt;/b&gt;5: A diagram depicting RSA and AES being used to-
gether for secure communication, based on informa-
tion in RSA vs AES - A Primer [21]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;421-the-algorithm&quot;&gt;4.2.1. The Algorithm&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RSA algorithm relies on two simple mathematical
facts [22]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiplication is easy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Factorisation is hard
The algorithm relies on modular arithmetic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A public
and private key are generated from two sufficiently
large prime numbers using the following process [24]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose large &lt;em&gt;p, q&lt;/em&gt; ∈ &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let n = pq&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let &amp;amp;straightphi;&lt;em&gt;(p, q) = (p − 1)(q − 1)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose e such that e is coprime to &amp;amp;straightphi;&lt;em&gt;(p, q). e&lt;/em&gt; is
usually chosen to be &lt;em&gt;65537&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt; are usually
chosen such that &amp;amp;straightphi;&lt;em&gt;(p, q)&lt;/em&gt; is coprime to &lt;em&gt;65537&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calculate d such that &lt;em&gt;de&lt;/em&gt; ≡ &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(mod&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp;straightphi;&lt;em&gt;(p, q))&lt;/em&gt;, that is
the modular inverse of &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The public key is &lt;em&gt;(n, e)&lt;/em&gt; and the secret key is &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A numerically encoded message be encrypted using
the public key, yet it can only be decrypted using the
private key. The following process is used to encrypt,
send, and decrypt a message using RSA keys[22]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assume we have a numerically encoded message &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assume further we have a public key &lt;em&gt;(n, e)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compute &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; ≡ &lt;em&gt;me (mod n)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send c, our cyphertext.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To decrypt, compute &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; ≡ &lt;em&gt;m (mod n)&lt;/em&gt; where &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; is
the original message, and &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; our private key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only known method to crack an RSA key is to
attempt to factorise our public key, to find d. This
is computationally complex. To give an example, in
2010 the record for cracking a 786-bit RSA key (that
is, a 232-digit number) was 2 years. They researchers
claim the amount of CPU time spent is equivalent to
2,000 years on a standard PC at the time [25]. It is
worth noting that the longer the key, the longer the
calculation take, but also the longer it takes to crack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;44-hashing&quot;&gt;4.4. Hashing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far in this section we have considered methods of
encryption where the encryptor wants a reciever to be
able to read the original data. Suppose we return to
example 2 in section 4.1. If the company had encrypted
their passwords, no attacker could get them. However,
if they had used a method we have discussed, and
attacker could find the key, they would still be able
to decrypt the passwords. Instead, they should use
hashing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hashing is a one way algorithm is used to convert
data into a hashed string. It is not possible to get back
to the original data from the hashed string. A hashed
password would be stored in the database, and when
the user tries to login, their input is hashed by the same
algorithm. If it matches the one stored on file they are
allowed in [26].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;441-plain-text-passwords&quot;&gt;4.4.1. Plain Text Passwords&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may surprise the reader to learn that even some major businesses 
have neglected to encrypt passwords and
users passwords have been leaked as a consequence.
Some notable organisations who have fallen foul of
this include the IEEE (2011) [27], Yahoo (2012) and
Hotmail (2009) [28]. This makes it particularly easy
for an attacker to access people personal information
should they find access to the database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;45-significant-vulnerabilities&quot;&gt;4.5. Significant Vulnerabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the methods in this section are strong, they still
have vulnerabilities. Suppose an attacker gets hold of
the private key, they would be able to decrypt all data
being transmitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected in the not too distant future a new
technology (a quantum computer) would be able to
break 2048-bit RSA encryption 8 hours. While this
isn’t a threat now, there is a risk that once a computer
is capable of breaking RSA in such a short period of time
RSA would no longer be a useful form of encryption.
Should this be the case, we would need newer and
faster algorithms to encrypt our data [29].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to hashing, as discussed in the previous
subsection. While it is not possible to reverse the algorithm,
 there is still a vulnerability. Suppose an attacker
got hold of a list of hashed passwords, and knew the
algorithm used. They could uncover the passwords by
brute force. If the attacker hashed all possible commbinations,
and for each output checked the list of hashed
strings, whenever they find a match they would know
that they have found the password used to generate
that hash. By doing this they would be able to slowly
crack a list of hashed passwords [30].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-conclusion&quot;&gt;5. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this report, we have considerd a selection of key
encryption methods, some of which are in use today,
and some of which are no longer sufficiently secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that over time, as computers get faster and
more advanced, existing encryption methods become
easier to crack. However, at a similar rate more layers of
complexity can be added to existing methods without
increasing computation time, more methods can be
strung together, and methods emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likely that for the forseeable future the encryption
 landscape will remain the same, with algorithms
being phased out and replaced by newer algorithms,
and keys getting longer, as computers get faster. It is
likely that the only significant encryption vulnerabilities
 will arise from poor practice, and failing to encrypt
data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a concern that if a fully working
quantum computer could be developed too soon, keys
could be cracked too quickly. It is possible that standard
non-quantum computers would be unable encrypt data
with sufficiently long keys using the current methods
without adding significant time overheads. If this were
to happen, it wouldn’t spell an end to secure communication,
however it would make the tradeoff between security and efficiency more obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[1] Icitsuser, “The ancient cryptography history,” Feb 2017. [Online]. Available: http://www.icits2015.net/ancient-cryptography-history/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[2] J. M. Norman, “The skytale: An early greek cryptographic device used in warfare: History of information.” [Online]. Available: https://www.historyofinformation.com/detail.php?d=4168&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[3] [Online]. Available: http://mathcenter.oxford.emory.edu/site/math125/transpositionCiphers/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[4] C. Paar and J. Pelzl, Understanding cryptography: a textbook for students and practitioners. Springer, 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[5] “Substitution cipher.” [Online]. Available: https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/substitution%20cipher&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[6] C. Suetonius Tranquillus, A. Thomson, and T. Forester, The Lives of the twelve Caesars. G. Bell and Sons, 1893.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[7] B. Oktaviana and A. P. U. Siahaan, “Three-pass protocol implementation in caesar cipher classic cryptography,” IOSR Journal of Computer Engineering, vol. 18, pp. 2278–0661, 07 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[8] H. Editors, “Morse code and the telegraph,” Nov 2009. [Online]. Available: https://www.history.com/topics/inventions/telegraph&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[9] ——, “Enigma key broken,” Nov 2009. [Online]. Available: https://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/enigma-key-broken&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[10] D. NG, “Enigma machine from world war ii finds unlikely home in beverly hills,” Jan 2015. [Online]. Available: https://www.latimes.com/entertainment/arts/culture/la-et-cm-imitation-game-enigma-machine-david-bohnett-20150122-story.html&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[11] S. Singh and W. S. Festival, “The enigma machine explained,” May 2013. [Online]. Available:https://youtu.be/ASfAPOiq_eQ&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[12] Simplified circuit diagram of a 3-wheel Service Enigma. [Online]. Available: cryptomuseum.com/crypto/enigma/working.htm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[13] Flaw in the Enigma Code. Numberphile, Jan 2013. [Online]. Available: https://youtu.be/V4V2bpZlqx8&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[14] T. Sale, The US 6812 Bombe Report 1944 - DECODING GERMAN ENIGMA MACHINE MESSAGES. SIGNAL SECURITY DETACHMENT, 1944. [Online]. Available: https://www.codesandciphers.org.uk/documents/bmbrpt/usbmbrpt.pdf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[15] “What is sql injection? tutorial and examples: Web security academy.” [Online]. Available: https://portswigger.net/web-security/sql-injection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[16] “Announcing the advanced encryption standard,” Nov 2001. [Online]. Available: http://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/FIPS/NIST.FIPS.197.pdf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[17] R. Franklin, P. Editor, and T. Security, “Aes vs. rsa encryption: What are the differences?” Jul 2020. [Online]. Available: https://www.precisely.com/blog/data-security/aes-vs-rsa-encryption-differences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[18] AES Explained (Advanced Encryption Standard). YouTube, Nov 2019. [Online]. Available: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O4xNJsjtN6E&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[19] “Leonard adleman made rsa encryption history with his invention.” [Online]. Available:https://www.invent.org/inductees/leonard-adleman&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[20] Sam., “A complete explanation of rsa asymmetric encryption,” Feb 2020. [Online]. Available: https://medium.com/curiositypapers/a-complete-explanation-of-rsa-asymmetric-encryption-742c5971e0f&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[21] P. Townsend. [Online]. Available: https://info.townsendsecurity.com/rsa-vs-aes-encryption-a-primer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[22] “Rsa encryption.” [Online]. Available: https://brilliant.org/wiki/rsa-encryption/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[23] “Modular arithmetic,” Oct 2020. [Online]. Available: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modular_arithmetic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[24] G. J. Simmons, “Rsa encryption,” Aug 2012. [Online]. Available: https://www.britannica.com/topic/RSA-encryption&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[25] T. Kleinjung, K. Aoki, J. Franke, A. Lenstra, E. Thomé, J. Bos, P. Gaudry, A. Kruppa, P. Montgomery, D. A. Osvik, H. te Riele, A. Timofeev, and P. Zimmermann, “Factorization of a 768-bit rsa modulus,” Cryptology ePrint Archive, Report 2010/006, 2010, https://eprint.iacr.org/2010/006.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[26] D. Arias, “Hashing passwords: One-way road to security,” Sep 2019. [Online]. Available: https://auth0.com/blog/hashing-passwords-one-way-road-to-security/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[27] O. Williams, “Ieee data breach: 100k passwords leak in plain text [update],” Sep 2012. [Online]. Available: https://www.neowin.net/news/ieee-data-breach-100k-passwords-leak-in-plain-text&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[28] E. Bauman, Y. Lu, and Z. Lin, “Half a century of practice: Who is still storing plaintext passwords?” Ph.D. dissertation, 0AD. [Online]. Available: https://web.cse.ohio-state.edu/ lin.3021/file/ISPEC15.pdf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[29] C. Gidney and M. Ekerå, “How to factor 2048 bit rsa integers in 8 hours using 20 million noisy qubits,” 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[30] B. Haran, Password Cracking. YouTube, Jul 2016. [Online]. Available: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7U-RbOKanYs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[31] F. Wenneker, “Wenneker article latex template,” LaTeXTemplates. [Online]. Available: https://www.latextemplates.com/template/wenneker-article&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">As an assignment for one of my MSc modules I had to produce a report on cyber security. I chose to focus on encryption methods. This is the report I produced. It was graded distinction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Klotksi Problem</title><link href="/2020/10/28/klotski.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Klotksi Problem" /><published>2020-10-28T13:14:13+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T13:14:13+00:00</updated><id>/2020/10/28/klotski</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/10/28/klotski.html">&lt;p&gt;As part of my Masters degree I implemented a breadth first search algorithm to solve the Klotski problem.  The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schoolarchimedes.com/klotski&quot;&gt;Klotski&lt;/a&gt; problem is a problem where you are given a 5x4 grid, with 4 types of piece.  The aim of the puzzle is to remove the one large centre-piece from the board, while removing no others.  An example of this puzzle can be found here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solution uses a recursive search to find all possible moves for any given board.  It implements each move, then searches for any further moves for each new board.  This continues until a solution is found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find the solution in this way, we need to make 116 individual moves, and analyse 23,118 distinct board layouts. It takes my PC approximately 2.5 minutes to run.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">As part of my Masters degree I implemented a breadth first search algorithm to solve the Klotski problem. The Klotski problem is a problem where you are given a 5x4 grid, with 4 types of piece. The aim of the puzzle is to remove the one large centre-piece from the board, while removing no others. An example of this puzzle can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Othello (CLI)</title><link href="/2020/10/20/Othello_cli.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Othello (CLI)" /><published>2020-10-20T14:14:13+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-20T14:14:13+01:00</updated><id>/2020/10/20/Othello_cli</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/10/20/Othello_cli.html">&lt;p&gt;I built this simple Othello game with a mini-max ‘AI’ player after a conversation with a lecturer about the algorithm.  It is text based, and has a very basic, very simple interface, however it seems relatively good at beating me at 8x8 or 6x6 Othello.  That said, I have no experience playing Othello so that isn’t necessarily a great achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some future improvements which could be made include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A GUI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Difficulty levels for the ‘AI’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refactoring the code - it was very much hacked together in a couple of days, and I do not claim for one minute that the code is any good.  If I take this further I would definitely give it a re-write.  I would probably use OOP, and structure it in a way that I could set 2 ‘AI’s against each other if I wanted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is complete and has been replaced by a GUI project using pygame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;play&quot;&gt;Play&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game can be played in 8x8 and 6x6 mode.  6x6 is faster.  Simply change the line &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DIMS = &lt;/code&gt; (line 40 in the code) between 6 and 8 to change the board size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic Welcome Screen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Welcome to Othello.  Please select an option:
A - Play against the computer
B - Play against a friend
Q - Quit Game
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Board and move selection screen for the 6x6 game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Black's turn:
  A B C D E F
1 . . . . . .
2 . . . . . .
3 . . b w . .
4 . . w b . .
5 . . . . . .
6 . . . . . .
Please input a move in the following form: A1, or P for pass
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note, the game is not case sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;play-vs-computer&quot;&gt;Play vs Computer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer uses minimax algorithm to play the game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Currently scored based on number of available moves, with a weighting given to certain squares:
    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def scoreBoard(board, player, opponent):
  player_score = len(generateMoveList(board, player, opponent))*3
  opponent_score = len(generateMoveList(board, opponent, player))*3

  if (player_score == 0) and (opponent_score == 0):
      # Have reached game end
      winner = decideWinner(board)
      winner = winner[0]
      if winner[0].lower() == player:
          return 300
      elif winner[0].lower == opponent:
          return -300
      else:
          return 0

  for i in range(DIMS):
      for j in range(DIMS):
          if board[i][j] == player:
              player_score += GRADING_STRATEGY[i][j]
          if board[i][j] == opponent:
              opponent_score += GRADING_STRATEGY[i][j]

  return player_score - opponent_score
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the following grading strategy (for 6x6, similar matrix produced for 8x8):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[[10, -2, 1, 1, -2, 10],
[-2, -2, 1, 1, 1, -2],
[1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1],
[1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1],
[-2, -2, 1, 1, -2, -2],
[10, -2, 1, 1, -2, 10]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-player-mode&quot;&gt;2 Player Mode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two player mode allows two players on same computer to play&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">I built this simple Othello game with a mini-max ‘AI’ player after a conversation with a lecturer about the algorithm. It is text based, and has a very basic, very simple interface, however it seems relatively good at beating me at 8x8 or 6x6 Othello. That said, I have no experience playing Othello so that isn’t necessarily a great achievement.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hangman</title><link href="/2020/09/14/hangman.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hangman" /><published>2020-09-14T14:14:13+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-14T14:14:13+01:00</updated><id>/2020/09/14/hangman</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/09/14/hangman.html">&lt;p&gt;I built this game as a quick project for fun.  It is a CLI based Hangman game.  It has a large library of over 90,000 words to chose from (random words assigned each time) along with two difficulty settings.  I coded this in about a day, using it as an opportunity to learn more about Git.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">I built this game as a quick project for fun. It is a CLI based Hangman game. It has a large library of over 90,000 words to chose from (random words assigned each time) along with two difficulty settings. I coded this in about a day, using it as an opportunity to learn more about Git.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chess</title><link href="/2020/06/10/chess.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chess" /><published>2020-06-10T14:14:13+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-10T14:14:13+01:00</updated><id>/2020/06/10/chess</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/06/10/chess.html">&lt;p&gt;As a summer project I decided to build a GUI chess game using pygame.  With the exception of a Checkmate function, the 2 player local game works perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intention of this project was to learn pygame, and develop my programming skills, improve at Python, as well as learning a bit about OOP.  For this reason, the programming style develops throughout the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to revisit this in future and re-write it in a better style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A future direction would be adding network functionaliy, and potentially an AI chess engine to play against.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">As a summer project I decided to build a GUI chess game using pygame. With the exception of a Checkmate function, the 2 player local game works perfectly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simulations to Demonstrate Mathematics</title><link href="/2019/12/15/tech-in-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simulations to Demonstrate Mathematics" /><published>2019-12-15T13:14:13+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-15T13:14:13+00:00</updated><id>/2019/12/15/tech-in-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/12/15/tech-in-education.html">&lt;p&gt;These were a set of tools using JSXGraph for use in teaching Maths.
These tools were produced as part of a third year university project working towards a BSc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trig-graphs&quot;&gt;Trig graphs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demonstrate the link between sin and cos functions and a circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taylor-series&quot;&gt;Taylor Series&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plots a taylor series for a given function alongside the actual graph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;double-pendulum&quot;&gt;Double Pendulum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simulation of a double pendulum with any sets of initial conditions.  Using an implementation of 4th order Runge Kutta method to solve Hamiltons equations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools in their submitted form can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://robertpsoane.github.io/javascript-maths-tools/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert</name></author><summary type="html">These were a set of tools using JSXGraph for use in teaching Maths. These tools were produced as part of a third year university project working towards a BSc.</summary></entry></feed>